I am pilot of Evangelion Unit 01, Shinji Ikari!
As soon as we started our coverage, we felt something.
That we shouldn't have taken up meeting this man.
Why Ube?
It's a secret.
What's the reason?
What does Anno really want to do?
Nothing in particular.
Nothing comes to mind. I have no idea.
Films I find interesting don't become hits.
Blockbuster movies are not my taste.
That's not for me.
Hideaki Anno, 60.
He gave birth to the one and only movie.
The movie that changed Japanese film history and became a huge hit: Shin Godzilla.
A.T. field, full power!
Also, the anime that caused a world phenomena and changed anime history: Evangelion.
Even now, 26 years after the TV broadcast, its cult remains strong.
When I'm watching Eva, tears come out.
I've been watching it from before my kids were born.
I love it, so I can't wait for the new one to come out.
However, the truth about it was covered by a mysterious veil.
I thought an alien had come. An alien.
Kinda like a terrorist.
He doesn't just want to make something interesting.
How should one lead his life in these times
He's a unique person.
What kind of person is Hideaki Anno?
We heard that the legendary anime Evangelion would come to an end, and we asked for a coverage.
However, that was the start of many days of self torment.
You don't need to film this.
No need to film this.
Use only the good parts.
We're not so kind.
If that's so, then this project is over.
The coverage went on and on to become the longest in our TV series: 4 years.
Something unprecedented.
I chose to ignore the fact that my physical and mental health would be destroyed if I overdo it.
My top priority is to make something interesting.
Of course, we're also filming you when you're perplexed.
It's still not enough.
It's not enough?
Is it not interesting if it's the same as up until now?
What we filmed, was a man who doesn't hesitate to do what it takes to entertain the fans.
Probably
The one who is most emotional during these 25 years is Shinji.
The Hideaki Anno that nobody knew
will be revealed tonight.
The filming began 4 years ago.
2017, in September.
Please wait.
For the first time ever, a camera enters to film scenes of the making of Evangelion in close coverage.
Production was steadily progressing inside the studio Anno had set up together with creators anyone would be jealous of.
However, director Anno was not present.
Around what time is Anno coming here?
It's not really fixed.
I spot him here only from time to time.
I don't think he comes around so often.
I wish you good luck.
Anno appears unexpectedly like a phantom.
Nobody knows when he'd show up.
2 hours later
Good morning. It's nice to meet you.
He had silently appeared.
There's no need to film from here.
An enigmatic smile.
As the meeting begins
I'm hoping someone will offer an opinion.
If it's cool, maybe we could say it.
It's not clear if he's listening or not.
Wonder if it uses something like that.
I see.
Maybe inside there's a...
He doesn't show up the next day or the day after.
Apparently, there is another workplace where even his close colleagues haven't set foot in.
Always absent?
That's right.
It can't be helped.
Even if he turns up sometimes
Probably gonna sleep all day.
You don't get enough sleep?
There was something we had to check with Anno.
Is it decided that Evangelion is going to end this time?
Yes, it is.
The story will end.
Are you not fond?
Nope.
Will you come tomorrow?
No, I won't.
See you.
Anno was a man shrouded in mystery.
But his way of life was already a legend.
26 years ago, Anno was the director of the anime that caused a social phenomenon: Neon Genesis Evangelion.
I mustn't run away.
I mustn't run away. I mustn't run away. I mustn't run away. I mustn't run away.
A story about the 14-year old Shinji Ikari
who mounts a multipurpose humanoid decisive weapon called Evangelion
and gets involved in a battle with mysterious creatures known as Angels.
The unvarnished psychological characterization moved the hearts of the audience.
No! I don't wanna listen!
Someone, please be nice to me.
I fought so much until now. I'm fighting with all I've got.
Won't you cherish me? Won't you be nice to me?
What's distinct about Anno, is that he's a frank person.
A man of perennial youth.
Although he's already 60, he doesn't grow up.
He probably wanted to become an adult but he failed at growing up.
If you'd look at Shinji, he's the same.
He is like that, and his anime character is the the same.
I believe that it's because that suffering is shown in the film, that young people can relate to it.
The pain of living.
3 theatrical installments of the movies have been released up until now.
They became big hits drawing over 8 million people to cinemas.
But will the long awaited final movie actually be the end the story?
Newer depths drew near.
We came to understand standing as the filming went on.
With his new film, Anno is trying to substantially change the way anime is made.
I want to make the draft as small as I can.
Also, I don't want to create the draft layout in my mind.
Typically, an anime is made by first making a storyboard draft based on a script.
And the characters and backgrounds are done in accordance with it.
I can't run away, can't run away, can't run away.
However, Anno said he'd make the new film without a storyboard.
First, everyone wants to decide what they'll do.
They want peace of mind.
It's reassuring.
But actually, it's better not to have a storyboard.
How exactly does he plan to make it?
We got a clue to that a little over one month after our filming began.
I also brought these valuable items.
The main staff camp like canned sardines at a ryokan in Atami to devise the plot.
Everyone was holding the script Anno had worked on for 8 years.
Should I say "make it somehow like"?
Based on that they come up with their own ideas and present them to Anno.
What if this monster's color is seen?
If he just keeps on heading straight...
I see your point.
Hello.
You can sit in the back.
Anywhere's fine.
Was the one I sent you last time received?
It's this one.
And in at the very end...
But Anno doesn't really look into the ideas given to him.
I believe this is used as a place for sharing.
I don't really know now.
Shall we stop for the time being?
Yes.
Okay.
More time is needed.
Yes
There are quite a lot of ideas for Unit 02.
Which one could we go with for the draft?
I don't know.
I see.
Should we give it a try?
At least what we can work with.
Right now, I can't say.
He kept repeating he doesn't know now.
Recently, I had a dream I was going to the cinema to see the new Eva movie.
Even scenes I didn't know about...
Wasn't the plot ready?
But there were so many scenes I didn't know about.
Tell me about them.
Hey, it was really amazing.
So Unit 01 and 02 were there, and a huge cloud storms, and then they appear on top of a huge octopus.
I felt like Anno really did it this time.
An octopus would be difficult.
N I C R O
This is like a time-lapse.
No need to film me.
I'll be leaving.
Goodbye.
Almost nothing was decided the first day.
On the second day
He didn't even show up.
I really don' t know.
Does this mean we have to change our ideas?
He doesn't even say if it's OK or a no go.
That's so like him.
Often seen in Evangelion.
I wonder if he saw it.
When we talk while looking at it, he tells me "Now I know it's not this".
But he doesn't say why.
I don't know if I should swing it more to the left or to the right.
So I have no idea what to do.
Moreover, I was thrown off when I read the script.
I said "don't leave me alone!"
and I grabbed him like this.
In the end I want to...
Hello.
On the 3rd day
He appeared as if nothing had happened.
Did you film the outside?
Not yet.
It's going to pour soon.
It seems it'll rain more heavily soon.
Film when it's raining the most.
You can use it as an insert edit.
I want to have the battles in a more compressed manner.
How should I do it?
Unexpectedly, Anno showed us a reaction.
I want to do it in one cut as much as possible.
What I'm most worried about with one cuts is that a transition always becomes necessary.
And that transition becomes too long-winded.
Basically I want to go with just one shot.
Best if it can be seen in one shot.
Best if it's seen in one shot, and only after we've tried doing it in one shot and it doesn't work, is when we give up.
We need to make new discoveries like this.
Otherwise the audience won't be impressed.
It's limited to what I come up with.
More than 80 mm.
That's brutal.
You have to go out and film this once.
Yes
When it's raining the most.
Anno is striving for something that goes beyond human intelligence.
He would even push his staff to the limit to obtain that.
I wonder what will happen if I keep pushing them like this.
It's not interesting at all if simply make it the way I see it.
My ideas aren't all that interesting.
I prefer something that can overrule them.
He's a mysterious man, really.
I wonder how many people there are that actually understand Anno.
The only thing I know is that it won't be Evangelion if it's not a work written and made by Anno.
What kind of person...
a person like an Angel.
A cute Angel.
A big one, with long arms but a cute face and round eyes.
But when he's activated, he can blow away a whole city.
I think he's rather girlish.
He does have a boyish heart, but I feel like there is also a girl dwelling inside.
He's a girlish boy.
3 months passed since we started filming.
Anno was actively searching for new ideas.
Allow me to introduce the actors.
Anna Mizuno as Shinji.
Nice to meet you.
Let's begin. Test. Ready.
Start
Shinji
What are you sitting in the corner for?
Come over here! Now!
Motion capture is a technique that turns acting into data for purposes of animation.
However, what is one supposed to do when there is no storyboard draft?
We're looking for the angle. That's all we need.
It'll be an interesting shot if we can bring the camera to a right angle.
The angle is all we need.
You're just like her!
Anno was set on pursuing the entertaining aspect of the angle.
A forgotten item.
There are many missed calls by Suzuhara and Aida.
According to Anno, the angle is the essence of anime.
As long as the angle and editing is good, the animation can be still.
There's no need for it to move.
Does this pertain only to animation?
No, even for live-action.
Regardless of whether the actors can surprise you, if the angle and editing is well done, it'll be entertaining.
The main staff are the ones looking for the good angle.
Anno only watches over them.
Sorry, it was alcohol.
Could you try getting a good angle of the two and the 1.8 bottle?
It's fine if the camera shakes.
There's not even one good wideshot from the front.
There's almost none of these we can use.
This is pretty difficult, eh?
The filming went on for days but Anno didn't seem satisfied.
Isn't this enough?
No, keep looking for it.
Okay.
There's no need to film me. Film this.
It's actually difficult because we're overflowing with footage.
That's what Anno wants.
We have footage where we can't tell if's what we're after or we just filmed by chance.
Isn't that what's good about it?
He's happy if we have a lot of footage.
Don't you also feel like you want to try holding the camera?
Nah, I'm fine.
I leave it to them. It's better to have them do it than me doing it.
If I do it from the start, I have to do everything myself.
It'll be limited to only that.
Does it feel like you're filming something different from your ideas this time around?
That's why I'm doing this.
If I wanted to make it true to my ideas, it'd be faster to draw a storyboard.
If one tries to create from inside their head...
It's limited to the world inside their mind.
There's nothing from the outside.
I want to express with things beyond my mind.
Perhaps it's an antithesis to my inflated ego.
Animation is but a mass of ego.
Why did you think like that?
It's a secret.
A secret?
Yes.
He never reveals the important part.
However, we managed to catch a glimpse of his true intentions.
Alright.
Anno started to look for the angle himself.
Anno always thinks he should let others do it at first.
But that doesn't end up the case.
In the end he fills the gaps himself or he rewrites it.
I guess we haven't managed to make something Anno would be satisfied with.
My abs hurt.
He shifts into being a creator the moment he thinks "this way'd be better".
Anno's compulsive drive is enigmatic to even his staff.
His blade was also pointed at us.
It happened half a year after we'd begun filming.
Please excuse me.
We were called by Anno when there was something he minded about the coverage.
I heard that there was some concern on your end regarding the our documentary filming.
I would like to propose some things we could improve on if you tell us more about it.
Well, it can't be helped there's only one camera.
Well there's also the GoPro sometimes.
But basically, I'm bothered when you point the camera at me at times when it's pointless to do so.
You know, I'm not the center of all this.
I may be the producer and director, but I'm the type that likes to have others do the work on set.
Their bafflement at times is amusing.
There's no need to film me, as I know that what I'm doing is extremely specific.
The people around me who are having troubles should be focused on.
Actually, Tamota (the director) is filming quite a lot of that too, so naturally, we also have footage of their frustration.
It's not enough.
It's still not enough?
Nope.
It's not so important what I say, you could just put narration over that.
It'd be good if you express it through their reactions.
It's not fun if you make the same documentary you've made until now.
I want you to make an entertaining documentary, so that my work can also look interesting.
Then, at the studio editing room
I don't know.
Tsurumaki was drowning in the whirlpool of confusion due to the task Anno had given him.
Let's decide on the marriage tomorrow.
We have to delete this cut.
They were making a Previs.
It edits the motion capture images and shows a simulation of the complete state.
This is the indicator in filmmaking.
I love you.
I think this one looks better.
However, the initial process moved at a sluggish pace due to the number of angles.
Was this Old Lady B?
It's C.
I can't tell at all.
We've been making anime for tens of years now, so it's become a routine for all of us.
Including me, of course.
If we were to make Eva the way anime is made now, it will only be a continuation of the 3 movies we made so far.
We'd have merely made another film similar to those.
The probability of it becoming something new becomes extremely low.
I personally don't like that.
Anno had entrusted his main staff with the 30 minute A-part Previs of the movie.
But he didn't seem satisfied with how it's coming along.
What did you think of the Previs Todoroki and Tsurumaki made?
That there's a lot left to do.
Will you be the one doing it from now here?
Yes, because there's no time.
Will you choose the best parts of each of their work?
I'm not really sure.
Maybe I'll restructure it from scratch.
2019, March 19.
Anno enters the editing room.
I'll do it from start.
From the start, okay.
He says he'll do it all over with the editor.
Number 37 of this and
37, yes.
37, 39, and 43.
From here onward, it's Anno vs. himself.
A battle of how much he can drive up the film by relying only on himself.
Boring, so boring.
It's too ordinary.
Is this okay?
It's okay? It isn't strange?
Uh, it's fine.
It's alright.
You not only film, you edit too right? Will you help us out?
Oh no, no, no.
Tell me if you get an idea.
Despite all of these, the angles are still not enough.
That night we were asked to join Anno for dinner for the first time.
Why did you decide to accept a documentary coverage this time?
Business purposes.
I expected that answer.
The film'll be left out if it remains shrouded in mystery.
I need to reveal a bit that the making process was interesting.
Maybe it's an age when things don't go well.
There are fewer people now that enjoy things shrouded in mystery.
I see.
Just one more glass.
Excuse me.
And cup of tea.
Tea? Okay.
Do you take pride in this anime for making a name for yourself?
No.
You don't?
It's not business where you boast about it.
Is that so?
But haven't you changed a lot of people's life?
I have to apologize for that.
It might have been for the better for some of these people, but it could have also been for the worse.
So I can't say anything.
I hope it was for the best.
It was after that
Anno locked himself into the editing room.
And plunged into a boundary known to none.
He has to overcome all the difficulties with his own strength since he set the bar so high for his staff.
For several days, the work continued until the late night.
No good.
I'm losing sight of how the angle should be.
Anno put all his physical and mental strength into it and started and fought with his back against the wall.
The first glimpse of him like this.
There was a worrying scene.
The protagonist Shinji is brought down to roam alone.
His ideas are all predictable, regardless of what he attempts.
I'll go look for some photos.
He said something bizzare.
A scene where he roams alone only inside a tunnel.
We'll try binding them together with half close-ups when he enters the tunnel.
In different tunnels?
Yes, different tunnels.
He say he'll express the emotions only with tunnels.
He enter from here.
I suddenly thought that the inside of a tunnel is fine.
Let's see how it turned out.
I feel like we went further than I thought we could.
It's only a tunnel, though.
We'll structure it with this.
Let's take a break.
If we do it the usual way, only normal plain shot flows will arise.
It's not that normal shot flows are bad.
But the problem is that it takes a lot of work, yet it's still not interesting.
It has to have a sort of bold "so-what" attitude to be entertaining.
However, 2 months later
Anno gathered the main staff at a meeting and said the following.
I'm thinking of rewriting the whole A-part if it isn't going well.
He said he would redo 1/4 of the script intro, that had been worked on for 9 months.
Basically I realized that my script hasn't been done properly thanks to this.
I want to rewrite it from square one.
Preferably from zero, even.
I'll start with whether A-part is even needed or not.
Going straight into B-part might be better.
Some of the staff gave negative comments about the Previs when he showed it.
Regardless how small that remark might have been, Anno cannot turn his eyes away from it.
We did our best and if this is the result we got, then maybe we should try better.
Anno is supported by one principle.
My work, comes before my life.
I think it's called placing the work above everything else.
I'm not the center, my work is.
It depends which is better for my work.
If I put my work and myself on a scale, my work would be heavier.
It's because I want to complete my work, even if it costs me my life.
You can't really do that after you've gotten married, but there is still an element of that.
Anno disappeared from the studio.
He shut himself inside his secret work space and started refining A-Part all over again.
The schedule has been pushed way back.
It can't be helped, let's just separate A-Part's scenes.
The script rework was exceptionally large.
I don't know what'll happen.
I don't know how I should direct that part.
However, anyone who cannot devote his whole body and soul to the project, has no place here.
It finally started to become an interesting documentary, eh?
This is too true to be funny.
It's too true to be funny as a production.
What are you going to do?
Still, it's how things always are here.
Always? Really?
It's the last one. And we don't want to have any regrets.
Have to give it all we've got.
Anno pushes you around but you still continue to work with him.
Why is that?
I wonder why.
Only now that you've asked me that I'm wondering now.
It might be because he lets us do what we want to do the most.
If you look at other places, for better or worse, the plan is more firm.
So you're never asked to do anything more than that.
But that's not to say that this is the better way of working.
At least I can't say that.
If it were any other director, he'd go with this.
This is boring.
Boring too.
Boring also.
This is how Anno's filmmaking progresses.
He denies himself and appears to hurt himself.
Hayao Miyazaki has spoken such of Anno.
Anno makes a movie while shedding his blood.
Anno's wife Moyoko on Hideaki Anno
I thought he'd die cause all he does is work and doesn't take care of himself.
He's abandoned life, or rather, living properly.
"No one to take care of you? Then I'll do it!" is what I offered.
But food was the most difficult part.
I can't eat this (shiitake mushrooms).
Also, this.
Quite a picky guy when it comes to food, and doesn't eat meat or fish.
For example, at first he didn't want to eat zucchini.
So I carefully explained that this is like a vegetable halfway between a cucumber and a pumpkin.
And told him he can eat cucumbers and kind of likes pumpkin too.
So I assured him it's not scary.
He's really cautious towards things he doesn't know.
It was kind of like disciplining, well not disciplining, but having an animal that doesn't really like humans to get used to them.
But if I hadn't done what I did, I think he would have died from some disease before that.
Really.
All he ate was sweets.
He eats a lot while editing.
Secretly from me, but I always find out right away.
He thinks he's the easily forgivable type.
So sometimes I tell him not to make a cute face.
Don't think I'll forgive you just because you think you're cute.
Anno's hometown: Ube, Yamaguchi.
His work above his own life.
How did that hard-fought way of life come into being?
Anno was born in 1960.
And there was something he missed since childhood.
The memory of going on a trip with his family.
This is an important photo.
His father Takuya lost his left leg in an accident and was not able to go out far away.
My dad hated the way the state of the world.
The incident where he lost his leg was also not his fault.
There were two people were standing on both sides,
cutting a big tree like this.
And that's when the incident happened as he was holding the saw.
Apparently, it was the other guy that made a mistake.
That mistake cost my father's leg and he had to visit doctors all his life.
So he bears a strong hatred towards society.
He also bounced his grudge off of me, questioning why he was the one to experience such misfortune.
In order to fill what he was missing, Anno looked to the television.
The first thing he became obsessed with was Tetsujin 28-go.
He didn't just watch the show, he also started drawing it.
There was one unique thing about his drawings.
When I draw a robot, he never has arms or legs.
I like the broken ones that have them detached.
Tetsujin 28-go often had his limbs torn, so maybe that's what I like about robots.
I now think my father is the reason why I think that some part should be missing.
There were many things missing in my everyday life. And one of them was my father.
So that was the basis for my feeling that not having everything together is better.
Maybe that's how I want to affirm my father as being such.
Anno continued to draw as if he were obsessed by something.
After graduating high school, he entered Osaka University of Arts.
By that time, he had become able to draw anime that outshines those done by pros.
The anime he made with his friends became a sensation.
He's bad at drawing people, but a genius at drawing explosions.
Osamu Tezuka was also astonished at his artistic talent.
And when he was 23 years old, he met that man.
I thought an alien had come. An alien.
From the moment I first saw him I thought he was interesting. So I got him to do it.
Hayao Myazaki entrusted him with the climax scene of "Nausicaa of the Valley of the Wind".
The explosion of the melting Giant God Warrior.
This is my genga(key animation).
The thoroughly drawn genga that needed no editing impressed Miyazaki.
He started living in the studio.
I wonder how many hours he worked in one day.
In the morning when I come, his bare feet would stick out from beneath the desk.
They were so dirty, I'd call them the feet of a cave man.
He's that kind of man.
Nadia, look, we're flying.
Amazing, we're actually flying.
He debuted as a director at 28 and gave birth to a hit anime.
And at 33 he kickstarted that project.
Neon Genesis Evangelion.
He developed a desire to draw humans.
It meant pouring his whole existence into his work.
What's wrong with that? What's wrong with running away from unpleasantness?
A protagonist who yearns to have his existence recognized.
Shinji-kun!
I'm not a child.
All the important characters were imperfect, and were missing something.
You won't even hold me!
No one! No one! No one!
So look at me!
I think it's interesting if an originally perfect subject is in some way broken.
I believe that defines interestingness.
Even if I make it beautiful it won't become interesting. All it would be is beautiful.
Well, my definition of interesting is somewhat twisted.
Lovable, because there's something missing.
That scene went against the accepted norms.
It felt like it's okay for his life to end here.
Because he's making something that will last forever, or have an influence on somebody,
at that time he had fully thrust himself into working with the preparedness and vigor to give his life for it.
He almost never left the director's room.
But he didn't eat fish or meat, so even though he didn't take a shower, he didn't smell.
Well, he did smell, but since he's vegetarian, it was more like the smell of a hen house.
Something unexpected happened after pushing himself and others to the limit.
The production couldn't meet the schedule.
The drawings that resembled a sketch with lines ended up being different than what had been planned.
It's the world around you.
It's not my world. I don't know!
There's no way I can cherish it!
Congratulations. Congratulations.
Thank you.
The ending presented many spectacles.
Congratulations.
Evangelion caused a social phenomenon and became a legend of an anime.
However, there was a critical outcry from some of the fans that Anno had abandoned his creation.
I believe I did my best for all the people over the world who love anime.
But there were discussion threads with the title "How to kill Hideaki Anno".
And inside them was written how to kill me in the most efficient way.
Kill me in this way, or that way.
When I saw that I stopped caring.
I kind of thought I didn't want to make anime anymore.
One time I thought of jumping in front of a train. And one time off the rooftop of my company building.
Around 2 times I faced this danger.
Was there a reason that stopped you from doing it?
I thought it'd hurt.
I was fine with dying but didn't want to die in pain. I thought about it realistically and gave up.
There was one person who reached out to Anno.
Producer Suzuki Toshio, whom he had met during the production of Nausicaa.
His heart was somewhat in pain.
So I thought that trying to make something would be the best medicine.
To make a step forward means to plan out a project.
After receiving help from Suzuki, he did a live-action movie set in his hometown of Ube.
What are you doing?
Maybe it's best if I don't exist.
And he took up making anime again.
But deep inside his heart there were emotions he couldn't get rid of.
If I had done everything, it'd be a rehash of Evangelion.
It would be a self-parody of Evangelion.
I already put everything I thought was entertaining inside Evangelion.
So if I tried to insert something new I believe is interesting, it'd end up being an Eva-esque work.
Anno wasn't able to escape from Evangelion.
In order to settle that feeling, he decided to remake it in the form of an anime movie.
But after producing 3 movies and taking up production of the final one, the one thing he had feared happened.
Anno broke down.
He could no longer come to the studio.
Depression
I broke down.
What is it that's breaking you down?
It's because I throw up everything.
I have to devote my whole body and soul to make it interesting.
I must do everything that I can.
I want to create something that's as entertaining as possible.
There was one person that stood next to Anno and supported him.
I believe that you can be saved as long as there's someone by your side.
I said
that even if everyone fades away,
I won't.
Regardless of how much he gets depressed or says he's had enough
even when he says he'll give up everything and goes somewhere
he'd start it over.
I believe he'll start creating again with a face as if nothing had happened.
Because he can only live this way,
he can't go on if he doesn't complete that work.
He keeps saying it's "work", but I do believe it's what he really wants to do.
Of course, I'm like that too.
Still,
He loves creating something.
Anno took up the production of Evangelion once again, as 4 years went by.
Ready. Go.
I couldn't bring myself to give up.
I thought I couldn't make it, but I never said to myself I don't want to make it.
I started this, so it's my duty to finish it.
A duty to myself, to my staff and above everything else, to the fans.
A duty to finish it
Anno was too honest of a person.
A naked soul in pain.
But that's exactly why that movie moves the hearts of people.
I believe it will properly end this time.
It will end and I will be able to end it.
I think it's because I was able to grow up a little.
Because my situation and my work are linked.
Things go in a positive direction.
That has to be the case within me too.
Or else, it will all be a lie.
The work is made true, because my inner world is part of it.
2018, Winter.
The movie was steadily approaching completion.
...is what couldn't be said about Evangelion.
I don't know what you're trying to do.
The D-Part of the script, which accounted for 1/4 of the final sequence, was not firmly decided on yet.
If you explain too much...
I, personally, thought I was better understood.
I'm in a pinch now because I learn that I wasn't understood at all.
Because I'm not being understood.
There was one year and a half left until the planned premiere of the film at this point.
But Anno announced he would redo it from the script.
This isn't good.
It's pretty tough with the change in schedule.
Probably the worst situation we've been in yet.
2 months passed
However, the script was not yet done by Anno.
Up until now, we want to show only what we've come to terms with.
Even if that takes time.
But still, we have a time limit.
I don't get any ideas.
For whatever reason, God doesn't want to appear before me.
The dubbing of the first half began even though the script for D-part wasn't complete.
I don't know.
What would Rei Ayanami do?
I want to tone down the intonation on the "do" to make it less assertive.
Cause she's hesitant.
I don't know. What would Rei Ayanami do?
Better, but...
I want more lack of confidence.
I don't know. What would Rei Ayanami do?
Should we keep it?
Keep it.
It's only good for a keep.
Give it some more.
With less confidence?
No, the confidence level is fine.
What's wrong?
Something's not there.
Anno's face became sterner as the days passed.
Please go ahead.
I'm okay.
The question was how true he could remain to his work.
Can he preserve himself at the cost of hurting others?
It's not entertaining as a whole.
I want you to move back here.
Okay.
And here you're going far too back.
Ah, yes.
Here you're too close.
I get the feeling that it's all backwards.
I got what the previous take is doing.
Do you still feel up to the challenge?
Yes.
Yes. I will do it.
I got not choice but to do it.
I also tell Anno often.
That I'll do my best. I'll do my best even if I have to sacrifice my life.
That's what it takes to make a work.
It's what it means to create something.
I think that all a movie director needs is guts.
Whether you have the guts to accept being blamed for everything.
It means not to be satisfied.
I want to continue seeking.
I don't want to end just cause it's good to a point.
Where do you draw the line?
The deadline.
Anno completed the D-Part script barely before the deadline.
He gathered the main staff and said:
Since we hardly have any time
If D-Part isn't wrapped up by the end of May, we won't make it in time.
Never gonna make it.
Right.
I personally believe this is the deadline.
The main priority is to complete it.
No matter what, this film has to be completed.
The man who had given his life for the sake of a high quality work, showed a fire in his eyes to complete it.
We saw him like that for the first time.
Anno is carrying a heavy burden too.
Being told by the fans, things like "you didn't finish it after all,"
or "I'll wait, no matter how many years it takes," is a heavy burden for him.
I think he wants to finalize the production because he wishes to move on or remove that burden and feel lighter.
From where?
Page 6 of D-Part.
The D-Part script was in handed to the voice actors.
Each of their characters' stories was drawing its end.
Unit 01 pilot, there's something I want to show you.
This is...
Doesn't a new story begin from here onward at the end?
No, it doesn't.
It's sad, but it's time to graduate.
Graduation has to happen one day.
My Eva ends with this.
Here, as long as you accept it, it's fine.
Because this is the end.
If you want to cry about it, that's fine.
Looks good.
Very good.
What should I do.
I thought the one now was pretty good.
What should I do...
I really don't want to cry too much.
Do it as you like.
Make me cry.
Please make me cry.
If it's you, it's possible.
I'll pilot the Eva.
Even if people hate me or talk bad about me,
none of it matters if I'm in the Eva
I'm only good for that, after all.
The quarter-century of pushing others and being pushed to the limit, comes to an end.
Anno added a line to the protagonist Shinji's part.
Farewell,
to all of Evangelion
Wrapping up all these 25 years.
All those in 25 years
Oh no, that's heavy!
If you could put all your feelings into this 25-year farewell.
Rolling.
What to do...
Alright.
Farewell, to all of Evangelion!
We can go with this.
I feel you gave it your all. Thank you.
Yes, that's good.
Thank you.
Good job.
You too.
At the end of 2020, the film was complete.
Thank you for your hard work. It's finished.
Thank you very much.
We asked Anno something after the sleepless night.
Can I ask something?
Yes.
You mentioned you put your life on the line for your work.
Why do you do that?
Because I can't do anything else.
Why do you go that far?
How should I put this...
Because that's all I can do to be of use to society.
That's what my purpose in this world is limited to.
Thank you for all your hard work throughout these years.
One more brief thing.
Thank you so much.
Enjoy.
Aren't you going to watch it?
No.
Why is that?
I never watch it.
I see.
Is there a reason?
Not really.
When it's completed, I need to move on to the next work.
I don't know.
What would Rei Ayanami do?
I'll remove it from the 3rd ship.
Full speed ahead.
Understood.
After it's completed, I just want people to be glad they made it.
That's all I can give them in return.
It was fun.
Thank you.
I'm glad we could do it.
I was about to cry.
I'd been glad if you did cry.
Wife
Moyoko Anno
What does it mean to be a professional?
I've never thought about that.
It doesn't really matter.
if you're called a pro or not.
I've always hated that the word is attached to this program.
I wish you'd put another title.
Thank you.